Register of the Evgenii Miller Papers, 1916-1924
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1924
  - (Group III, File 26M) (Box 12.)
    - Rossiiskoe Obshchestvo Krasnago Kresta
      - Printed matter
        - Apercu de la situation de la Croix Rouge Russe a la fin de l'annee 1921 (Folder 12)
        - Otchet o deiatel'nosti Glavnago Upravleniia i mestnykh Predstavitel'stv za granitsei, po 1-e iiulia 1922 (Folder 13)
        - Les refugies russes dans la region de Constantinople au mois de juin 1921 (Folder 14)
        - Bulletin Officiel, 1922 (Folder 15)
    - Reports
      - "Otchet o deiatel'nosti Glavnago Upravleniia R.O.K.K. za vremia s 1-go marta po 1-oe noiabria 1921 goda". Typescript (Folder 16)
      - "Zagranichnaia pomoshch golodaiushchim v Rossii". Also includes open letter of Mezhdunarodnaia kommissiia pomoshchi golodaiushchim to Soviet Foreign Minister Georgii CHicherin. Typescript (Folder 17)
    - (Group III, 27M)
      - France. Ministere de la Guerre, 1921-1923. Correspondence of Gen. SHCHerbatchev, Lieut.-Gen. Ivan Miller and others with Gens. Desticker and Weygand and the Ministere de Guerre, the Etat Majeur de l'Armee, Bureau Slave and the Comite Militaire Allie de Versailles
        - General office correspondence. Includes situation of Russian officers in France and repatriation of military personnel who had served on Western Front; Russian officers in transit from the Baltic and other fronts, closing of Russian Military Mission in Peking. Typescript (Folder 18-20)
        - Individual cases involving former Russian officers. Includes questions related to documentation, the education of Russian officers in French military schools and enquiries re missing persons. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 21-22)
        - Military situation of anti-Bolshevik forces on the Polish Front and the Crimea. Includes telegrams, transcripts of telegrams and bulletins re situation on Crimean front; negotiations for aid from French government; transportation of supplies and personnel. Typescript (Folder 23-26)
        - Soviet Union. Miscellaneous material re purchase of supplies. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - (Group III, File 28M) (Box 13.)
    - France. Ministere de la Guerre, 1919-1923
      - Appeals
        - Comite Parlementaire Russe a Paris to French president. Typescript (Folder 1)
        - Vrangel', Petr Gen. et al., "Aux Peuples de l'Univers!". Typescript (Folder 2)
      - Correspondence. Includes letters of Gens. Foch and Weygand
        - General office correspondence. Includes material re situation of Russian military personnel in France; repatriation of Russian military personnel (Kabadzha Camp). Typescript and handwritten (Folder 3-4)
        - Individual cases. Includes questions related to recruitment of Russians into the French Foreign Legion; acceptance of Russians into French military schools; documentation of Russian military personnel in France; missing persons. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 5-9)
        - Supply and financial matters. Typescript (Folder 10)
      - Decorations and citations received by Russian troops from French government. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - (Group I, File 29M)
    - Ministerstvo Innostrannykh Del and other Russian diplomatic agencies, 1920-1923
      - Correspondence. Includes correspondence of Grigorii Aleksinskii, Nicholas de Basili, Mikhail Girs, Aleksandr Neratov and Petr Struve
        - General office. Includes administrative and financial matters. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 12-13)
        - Individual cases. Includes requests for visas and other documents and inquiries re missing persons. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 14-16)
        - Military matters. Includes telegrams and transcripts of telegrams re situation on the Crimean and Polish fronts. Typescript (Folder 17-18)
        - Resettlement and supply of military and civilian refugees. Includes material re cadet schools; supply of hospitals on Gallipoli, Lemnos and in Yugoslavia; activity of Komitet po Delam o Bezhentsakh Severnoi Oblasti and Biuro Trudovoi Pomoshchi pri Rossiiskoi Missii v Afinakh. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 19-21)
        - Supply. General. Typescript (Folder 22)
        - Transfer of military personnel to the Crimean front. Includes information re Far Eastern troops interned in China; situation of Russian troops in Estonia; repatriation of Russian military personnel by France and situation of Soviet prisoners of war in Germany. Also see individual cases, above. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 23)
      - Reports re disposition of Soviet Army and political situation in Poland. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - (Group I, File 30M)
    - Finansovo-Kontrol'naia Komissiia pri Rossiiskom Posol'stve vo Frantsii, 1919-1923
      - Correspondence
        - General office correspondence re financial matters. Includes financing of Russian military agencies, military schools, hospitals and homes for invalid servicemen. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 25-29)
        - Archive of Russkii Ekspeditsionnyi Korpus vo Frantsii. Miscellaneous material re its relocation. Typescript (Box 14., Folder 1)
        - Individual cases. Includes reimbursement of individuals for expenses and losses suffered while on military duty. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 2-4)
        - Military supplies. Typescript (Folder 5)
      - Minutes of meetings. Typescript (Folder 6-7)
  - (Group I, File 31M)
    - Turkey. Rossiiskii Voennyi Agent v Turtsii, 1920 July-1921 Sept.
      - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
        - General correspondence of central office with Russian representatives abroad. Includes material re maintenance of Russian administration in Turkey (Folder 8-9)
        - France. Ministere de la Guerre and other military administrative bodies (Folder 10)
        - Military
          - General. Military personnel
            - Evacuation (Folder 11)
            - Individual cases (Folder 12)
            - Maintenance (Folder 13)
            - Repatriation (Folder 14)
            - Transfer (Folder 15)
          - Reports. Includes material re Communist Party in Russia and Turkish military activity in Anatolia. Includes maps (Folder 16)
          - Telegrams, intelligence and information re military action and movement of troops in Crimea; creation of Polish Third Army. Includes telegrams from Sevastopol' (Folder 17)
        - Politics. Political activity of emigre committees and groups (Folder 18)
        - Press. Bulletins of "Biuro Russkoi Pechati v Konstantinopole" (Folder 19)
        - Refugees (Folder 20)
        - Supply, transportation and communications (Folder 21)
    - (Group I, File 32M)
      - Turkey. Rossiiskii Voennyi Agent v Turtsii, 1921-1923
        - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
          - General. Includes diplomatic and military matters; evacuation and settlement of military refugees (Folder 22-23)
          - Bulgaria (Folder 24)
          - Denmark. List of Russian military buried in Helsingfors (Folder 25)
          - Gallipoli. Press re executions on Gallipoli (Folder 26)
          - Germany. Includes material re Army of Gen. Bermondt and Russian prisoners of war (Folder 27)
          - Imperial family, assassination. Includes letter of N. Sokolov (Folder 28)
          - Italy (Folder 29)
          - Medical institutions (Folder 30)
          - Military academies and education (Folder 31)
          - Poland. Includes material re Boris Savinkov, Gen. Petr Makhrov, the Russian Third Army and Tukhol' Internment Camp (Folder 32)
        - Printed matter, Russkii Komitet v Turtsii. Materialy po voprosu ob evakuatsii russkikh bezhentsev iz Konstantinopolia (Folder 33)
        - Reports, including on Belorussia, Turkey and Anatolia. Includes transcripts of Soviet radio. Typescript (Folder 34)
  - (Group I, File 33M)
    - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1919-1921 (Box 15.)
      - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
        - General, including Baron Petr Vrangel' (Folder 1)
        - Administration. Includes instructions to Military Representatives (Folder 2)
        - Awards. Russian medals to foreigners (Folder 3)
        - Cossacks (Folder 4)
        - Estonia (Folder 5)
        - Japan (Folder 6)
        - Military personnel. Includes material re transfer of officers to Crimea; missing persons (Folder 7-10)
        - Poland. Includes correspondence of Gen. Petr Makhrov (Folder 11)
        - Refugees (Folder 12)
        - Supplies, finances, communication and transportation. Includes material re navy and commercial fleet (Folder 13)
      - Declaration of Baron Petr Vrangel' re his policies. Printed copy (Folder 14)
      - Orders. Military and military personnel (Folder 15)
      - Reports. Includes intelligence re conditions on military fronts, interviews with eyewitnesses from the Soviet Union; conditions of life for refugees. Typescript (Folder 16-17)
    - (Group I, File 34M)
      - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1921
        - Addresses. Printed copies
          - Antonii (KHrapovitskii), Metropolit (Folder 18)
          - Semenov, Ataman (Folder 19)
          - Vrangel', Baron Petr (Folder 20)
        - Correspondence
          - General (Folder 21)
          - Administration of Military Representatives (Folder 22)
          - Awards (Folder 23)
          - Cossacks (Folder 24)
          - Czechoslovakia (Folder 25)
          - Military personnel. Includes material re officers' associations (Folder 26)
          - Poland. Includes correspondence of Gen. Petr Makhrov (Folder 27)
        - Press. Includes press releases to Vladimir Burtsev and Pavel Miliukov (Folder 28)
        - Relocation, repatriation and maintainance of Russian troops. Includes correspondence with French authorities (Folder 29-30)
        - Russkii Sovet (Folder 31)
      - Orders (Folder 32)
      - Printed matter
        - Russkii Sovet, K voprosu o Russkoi Armii (Folder 33)
        - Russkii Zemledelets, Prague (Folder 34)
      - Reports (Folder 35)
  - (Group I, File 35M) (Box 16.)
    - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1921-1922
      - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
        - General (Folder 1)
        - Administration of Military Representatives (Folder 2)
        - Awards (Folder 3)
        - Committees, emigre organizations (Folder 4)
        - Cossacks. Open letter of Ataman Petr Krasnov (Folder 5)
        - Military personnel (Folder 6)
        - Military schools (Folder 7)
        - Poland. Includes material re Tukhol' internment camp; correspondence of Gen. Petr Makhrov (Folder 8)
        - Press. Includes material re monarchism (Folder 9)
        - Relocation and maintenance of Russian military, especially in the Balkans (Folder 10-11)
        - Supply. Includes negotiations with French government re naval compensation (Folder 12)
      - Orders (Folder 13)
      - Reports. Includes material re conditions in and relations with the Soviet Union. Typescript (Folder 14-15)
  - (Group I, File 36M)
    - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1922-1923
      - Administration. Includes material re Lieut.-Gen. IUrii Romanovskii (Folder 16)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 17)
        - Military personnel (Folder 18)
        - Military schools and education (Folder 19)
        - Monarchism (Folder 20)
        - Poland. Includes correspondence of Gen. Petr Makhrov (Folder 21)
        - Russian Army abroad. Includes material re employment and living conditions; aid to refugees; situation in Bulgaria and France (Folder 22)
        - Russian fleet (Folder 23)
      - Leaflets (Folder 24)
      - Orders and addresses (Folder 25)
      - Press and publications (Folder 26)
      - Reports. Includes material re situation in Soviet Union; conditions for Russian Army abroad; execution of Metropolitan Veniamin of Petrograd. Typescript (Box 17., Folder 1-5)
  - (Group I, File 37M)
    - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1923
      - Administration (Folder 6)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 7)
        - Committees, emigre organizations (Folder 8)
        - Education (Folder 9)
        - Germany (Folder 10)
        - Intelligence (Folder 11)
        - Military personnel (Folder 12)
        - Monarchism (Folder 13)
        - Poland. Includes correspondence of Gen. Petr Makhrov (Folder 14)
        - Press (Folder 15)
        - Russian Army abroad (Folder 16)
      - Orders (Folder 17)
      - Reports. Includes essays by IUrii Artsybashev and Sergei Mel'gunov (Folder 18)
  - (Group I, File 38M)
    - General Headquarters of Lieut.-Gen. Baron Petr Vrangel' and Russian Military Representatives, 1924-1925
      - Correspondence. Includes Voennyi Agent vo Frantsii, Lieut.-Gen. Evgenii Miller and Nachal'nik Gruppy Russkoi Armii vo Frantsii i Bel'gii, Lieut.-Gen. Pavel SHatilov. Typescript and handwritten
        - General. Includes administrative matters (Folder 19)
        - Military personnel (Folder 20)
        - Press (Folder 21)
        - Russian Army abroad. Includes reports re employment of military refugees, especially transfer from Bulgaria to France and Belgium; conditions of work in France (Folder 22-24)
      - Printed matter (Box 18.)
        - Informatsionnyi Biulleten' (Folder 1)
        - Vestnik Gallipoliitsev, No. 2 (Folder 2)
      - Reports. Typescript
        - General. Includes intelligence and material re employment of army abroad (Folder 3)
        - Miller, Lieut.-Gen. Evgenii, "O russkoi armii" (Folder 4)
        - "Svodka o zhizni chastei gallipoliiskoi gruppy v Bolgarii" (Folder 5)
  - (Group I, File 39M)
    - Imperial officers' organizations, 1919-1924. Correspondence
      - General, including on administration; work projects; intelligence (Folder 6)
      - Education (Folder 7)
      - Legal status of Russian officers in France (Folder 8)
      - Officers' organizations
        - Obshchestvo Gallipoliitsev vo Frantsii (Folder 9)
        - Obshchestvo Russkikh Ofitserov General'nago SHtaba (Folder 10-15)
        - Ofitserskaia stolovaia-obshchezhitie v gor. Parizhe (Folder 16)
        - Red Cross. Includes rules for obtaining exit visas from Soviet Union (Folder 17)
        - Russkii Soiuz Uvechennykh Voinov v Germanii (Folder 18)
        - Soiuz Ob"edinennykh Ofitserskikh Obshchestv and Obshchestvo Russkikh Ofitserov Artilleristov (Czechoslovakia) (Folder 19)
        - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov Uchastnikov Velikoi Voiny (Folder 20-21)
        - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov v Italii (Folder 22)
        - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov v Korolevstve Vengerskom (Folder 23)
  - (Group I, File 40M)
    - Russian Army abroad. Military and civilian refugees, 1919-1922
      - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
        - General. Includes administrative matters (Folder 24)
        - American Air Squadron (Folder 25)
        - Organizations (Box 19.)
          - Russkii Natsional'nyi Komitet and Russkii Sovet. Includes "Ocherki Politicheskoi ZHizni" (Folder 1)
          - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov, Uchastnikov Velikoi Voiny and Obshchestvo Russkikh Ofitserov General'nago SHtaba (Folder 2)
        - Press and publications (Folder 3)
        - Refugees, especially military. Includes list of aid organizations in Paris; activity of aid and other organizations; employment; individual cases (Folder 4-6)
        - Relations with French and international authorities (Folder 7)
        - Rossiiskoe Obshchestvo Krasnago Kresta (Folder 8)
        - Saloniki Front (Macedonia). Conflict re disposal of military chaplain's supplies (Folder 9)
        - Supply and finance (Folder 10)
        - Transfer of officers to Crimea and the Far East. Includes material re Rossiiskii Torgovyi Flot (Folder 11)
        - Ukraine (Folder 12)
      - Speech. Riabushinskii, P. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - (Group I, File 41M)
    - Russian Army abroad. Military and civilian refugees, 1922-1924
      - Appeals. Printed copies (Folder 14)
      - Correspondence. Typescript and handwritten
        - General (Folder 15)
        - Monarchism (Folder 16)
        - Organizations
          - General (Folder 17)
          - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov, Uchastnikov Velikoi Voiny and Obshchestvo Russkikh Ofitserov General'nago SHtaba (Folder 18)
          - Russkii Inzhenernyi Soiuz (Folder 19)
          - Russkii Natsional'nyi Komitet and Russkii Sovet (Folder 20-22)
        - Press and publications (Folder 23)
        - Refugees, especially military
          - General. Aid to groups and individuals; employment; missing persons. Includes letter of Ivan Bunin (Folder 24-26)
          - Kornilovskii Udarnyi Polk (Folder 27)
        - Relations with French and international authorities (Folder 28)
        - Sergievskoe Podvorie (Folder 29)
        - Speech, V. I. Gurko. Typescript (Folder 30)
  - (Group I, File 42M)
    - Osobaia Komissiia po razsledovaniiu zlodeianii bol'shevikov, sostoiashchei pri Glavnokomanduiushchem Vooruzhennymi Silami na IUge Rossii, 1918-1919. See PHOTOGRAPHS
  - (Group I, File 43M). See PHOTOGRAPHS
  - (Group I, File 44M) (Box 20.)
    - Bolshevik atrocities, 1918-1917
      - General
        - Sidorov, D. A., Organizovannye razstrely obshchestvennykh deiatelei v Moskovskoi Butyrskoi tiurme (Folder 1)
        - Surguchev, I., Bol'sheviki v Stavropole (Folder 2)
      - Osobaia Komissiia po razsledovaniiu zlodeianii bol'shevikov, sostoiashchei pri Glavnokomanduiushchem Vooruzhennymi Silami na IUge Rossii, 1918-1919. Printed matter
        - Pamphlets
          - Akt razsledovaniia o nasil'stvennom zakhvate vlasti bol'shevikami (kommunistami) v Stavropol'skoi gubernii (Folder 3)
          - Akt razsledovaniia o sotsializatsii devushek i zhenshchin v gor. Ekaterinodare po mandatam Sovetskoi vlasti (Folder 4)
          - Akt razsledovaniia o zlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov, sovershennykh v 1918 i 1919 godakh v Sviatogorskom Uspenskom monastyre Iziumskago uezda, KHar'kovskoi gub. (Folder 5)
          - Akt rzsledovaniia po delam o zlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov v 1919 godu v g. Novocherkasske i drugikh mestnostiakh Donskoi oblasti (Folder 6)
          - Akt razledovaniia po delu o neudavshemsia napadenii bol'shevikov na poezd Frantsuzskoi missii... (Folder 7)
          - Akt razsledovaniia po delu o vzryve bol'shevikami bomb na uchebnom sudne 'Rion ubiistvakh, sovershennykh bol'shevikami (kommunistami) v iiune-iiule 1918 g. v g. Stavropole (Kavkazskom) (Folder 8)
          - Akt razsledovaniia po delu o zlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov v stanitsakh Labinskago Otdela i v gor. Armavire (Folder 9)
          - Akt razsledovaniia po delu ob izbienii bol'shevikami v lazaretakh stanitsy Elizavetinskoi ranenykh i bol'nykh uchastnikov Dobrovol'cheskoi Armii (Folder 10)
          - Akt razsledovaniia po delu ob ubiistvakh, sovershennykh bol'shevikami v 1918 godu v gorode Rostove na Donu (Folder 11)
          - Izvlecheniia iz proizvodiashchagosia Osoboi Komissiei...razsledovaniia o bol'shevikakh v g. Poltave i Poltavskoi gubernii (Folder 12)
          - Soobshchenie o goneniiakh bol'shevikov (kommunistov) na tserkov' v Donskoi oblasti (Folder 13)
          - Spravka o sozhzhenii krasnoameitsami kazaka IAkova CHusa (Folder 14)
          - Svedeniia o razgrome bol'shevikami Taganrogskago Okruzhnago Suda (Folder 15)
          - Svedeniia o zlodeiianiiakh bol'shevikov na iuzhnom poberezh'e Kryma (gorod IAlta i eia okrestnosti) (Folder 16)
          - Svedeniia o zlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov v gor. Evpatorii (Folder 17)
          - Svedeniia ob arestakh, proizvodivshikhsia bol'shevikami v Stavropole Kavkazskom s 1 ianvaria po 8 iiulia 1918 g. (Folder 18)
          - Vypiska iz akta po delu o zlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov v g. IAlte i eia okrestnostiakh (zlodeianiia protiv musul'manskago naseleniia) (Folder 19)
          - Vypiska ob otnoshenii bol'shevikov k magometanskoi religii, iz dela ozlodeianiiakh bol'shevikov v Stavropol'skoi gubernii (Folder 20)
        - Poster, "Zverstva Bol'shevikov. Uzhasy khar'kovskoi chrezvychaiki" (Folder 21)
  - (Group I, File 45M)
    - Belgium. Rossiiskii Voennyi Agent v Bel'gii, Col. Andrei Prezhbiano, 1920-1921
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 22-24)
        - Belgian and French authorities (Folder 25)
      - Reports. Includes reports re Bolshevik activity in Europe (Folder 26)
    - Germany. Rossiiskii Voennyi Agent v Germanii, Col. Aleksei von Lampe, 1922-1923. Reports. Includes material re Russian officers' organizations; political situation in Germany and excerpts from German press (Folder 27-28)
    - Hungary. Rossiiskii Voennyi Agent v Vengrii, Lieut-Gen. Vladimir Marushevskii and Col. Aleksei von Lampe, 1920-1921
      - Correspondence. General. Includes material re Austria; French and international authorities (Folder 29-30)
      - Reports re Soviet-Polish relations. Typescript (Folder 31)
    - Romania. Correspondence, 1923 (Folder 32)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1916-1924.
  - 11 prints depicting Bolshevik atrocities. Evidence collected by the Osobaia Komissiia po razsledovaniiu zlodeianii bol'shevikov, sostoiashchei pri Glavnokomanduiushchem Vooruzhennymi Silami na IUge Rossii, 1918-1919. (File 42) (Folder fA)
  - 6 unidentified prints depicting aspects of the Russian Civil War, 1917-1921 (Folder B)
  - 22 prints depicting the Kornilov Exhibit, 1919 (Folder C)
  - 1 portrait print depicting Col. A. Bitenbinder (Folder D)
  - 1 portrait print depicting Lieut.-Gen. Anton Denikin (Folder E)
  - 1 print depicting Gen. Nikolai Ivanov, 1916. (Folder F)
  - 5 prints depicting Lieut.-Gen. Lavr Kornilov (Folder G)
  - 1 print depicting arrival of Lieut.-Gen. Aleksandr (Folder H)
  - 7 prints depicting Lieut.-Gen. Vladimir Mai-Maevskii in KHar'kov and Poltava, 1919 (Folder I)
  - 1 portrait print depicting Maj.-Gen. P. Nepenin (Folder J)
  - 1 portrait print depicting Vladimir Pedsovskii, Kuban (Folder K)
  - 1 print depicting the grave of Vladimir Purishkevich (Folder L)
  - 1 print depicting Gen. SHeidtman (Folder M)
  - 1 print depicting Maj.-Gen. Tretiakov (Folder N)
  - 2 prints depicting the cathedral in Ekaterinodar (Folder O)
  - 1 print depicting Novocherkassk (Folder P)
  - 3 prints depicting Taganrog during the Civil War (Folder Q)
  - 7 prints depicting White Russian officers of "Polk imeni Gen. Alskseeva" in Decazeville, France (Folder R)
  - 7 glass negatives depicting aspects of the Russian shelf Civil War in South Russia (Box 21)